[SPEAKER_02]: The simile of the six animals.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suppose, monks, a man catches six animals of different domains and different resorts.
[SPEAKER_02]: A snake, a crocodile, a bird, dog, a jackal and a monkey, tethering each with a strong rope.
[SPEAKER_02]: Having tethered them with a strong rope, he fastens the rope together in the middle.
[SPEAKER_02]: He lets go of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, monks, these six animals of different domains and feeding habits would swing around and struggle, each trying to get to the... to his natural domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: The snake would struggle, the crocodile and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, monks, when those six hungry animals grow weary, they would yield to the one that was the strongest, go his way and be under his power.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same way, monks, whenever a monk fails to practice and develop mindfulness as to the body, the eye struggles to draw him towards attractive objects, while unattractive objects are repellent to him.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, this monk is lack of restraint.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what monks is restraint?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, instead of... he ties all those animals to a strong post, and then they all pull in their different directions, grow tired, and stay right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that post is mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the... would you... can you have... the strain of the six senses, so including your mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: Without the... without the right context, without... like, if you don't have perspective, in regard to the... all of the six senses, so, without a perspective, can you restrain them?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because you're already pulled.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why non-perspective, lack of perspective, means you're down the the pull of a sense or all the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people don't have... like people who engage with sensuality, they would have called sensuality weakeners of wisdom, weakeners of perspective, weakeners of things that you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you get pulled down the... down the... the pathway of a sense, of that wild animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot sustain perspective and at the same time go down the rabbit hole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You either allow and go down the rabbit hole or you sustain the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason why I'm bringing perspective... the perspective up is because people would often think that mindfulness of the body means, like, feeling the body here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, feeling the sensations of it means I'm mindful of this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness of the body is the fundamental perspective in regard to your own world, as in the presence of the body there, as Satipaṭṭhāna Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the body there is the basis for these six animals, to which they are tied to, whether they want to or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have sense organ without the body, without a unit of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why mindfulness of the body would mean mindfulness of the perspective in regard to all the six.
[SPEAKER_02]: Senses that you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not a physical way of, like, method, practice of staying in the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of knowledge of the body there, its nature, its post, from which these senses want to pull left and right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, if you contemplate the nature of that body, as the Buddha would say, as something that is unownable, subject to illness, death and so on,
[SPEAKER_01]: No pleasure of the senses within the container of the body would be able to overwhelm that perspective, if it's thoroughly developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you see your body as not mine, that's the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, if you see the body on the right level as not mine, not just, oh yes, this body is not mine,
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you think you're seeing the body on the right level, as not mine, you see, while I'm seeing the body on the right level, as not mine, is there passion and liability to passion in this mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there aversion and liability to aversion in this mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there distraction and liability to distraction in this mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer to any of those is yes, that's not the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because seeing the body on the right level, it is impenetrable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you, with the mind not above passion, aversion, delusion and liability to passion, aversion, delusion, thinks this is the right level of the mindfulness of the body, well, you're confusing yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is a serious misconception, because of which you will then not make the effort to find what the right level is, the level that is not liable to greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in what way?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do we be mindful of the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, through understanding its... Well, one way would be through understanding its nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just through, like... Because, as I said, be mindful of the body and you have some idea about it and how you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead of focusing on doing the mindfulness of the body, focus on understanding the idea of what you think mindfulness of the body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people just take that idea for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I hear mindfulness of the body
[SPEAKER_01]: As an instruction, and whatever comes to my mind that I do, is mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, isn't that fortunate?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it were so.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you know, it's the idea, that's where the context, the right context, the wrong context, is basically right idea, wrong idea, or right ideas, wrong ideas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you're gonna have some notion of the mindfulness of the body and some notion of the sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to do it, in a sense of you have to be sensory-strained.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead of taking the notion for granted, through which you just keep doing this technique of mindfulness of the body or whatever it is for you, you actually keep dwelling on the notion and clarify it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it correspond to what the suttas describe?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it make you dispassionate completely?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when you are not momentarily focused on the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it an anchor that allows you to then move around dispassionate, not liable to anger, not liable to delusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it something that you're dispassionate and not angry and so on, only when you're focusing on the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, that's not mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just you replacing one object with the other object.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you've got to have some idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will have some idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then... but you can't forget about that idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to practice it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to be upgrading the idea behind
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you want to be developing understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just whatever you assumed mindfulness of body is, is what it is, and now you're just doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that mindfulness of the body were the correct mindfulness of the body, you would be at least anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would have no more central pull.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when the mindfulness of the body is understood to the extent necessary, you're enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people conflate understanding, like, fulfilling the understanding of mindfulness of the body in this case, with doing enough of mindfulness of the body that I just assumed mindfulness to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like, okay, maybe you were lucky, maybe your assumption of the mindfulness of the body was really correct right from the start, but what's the chance of that today?
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, how many years have you been doing it, and are there the results to show for, even when you're not mindful of the body with your effort?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's why people would also like fall into the view that, oh yeah, this is the dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because, yeah, there is no passion, and ill-will, and current delusion, when you're actively making this effort to be focused on body or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that object in itself of your focusing, yeah, it's not arising in passion and so on, but are you liable?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you stop the focusing, will the passion come back?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means there is no understanding that has taken root, which would have stayed, regardless of whether you're focusing on the body or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's same with the sensory strains.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the five animals, it's not just
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the problem, it's not that the five animals want to go and feed in these different domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that you don't know how to not identify with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you don't know how to not take them as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I want to see something, ears want to hear something, your first starting point is, I want to see something, I want to hear something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you hammer down the restraint on yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where restraint is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is an inherent discrepancy there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I say, you shouldn't be trying to get rid of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should restrain yourself, but you can only do that correctly on the basis of allowing these things to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your eyes want to see something.
[SPEAKER_01]: You restrain eyes from seeing, but you don't ignore the fact that eyes want to see something.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get to, basically, outline the domain of the eye, that you realize, ah, okay, this is what an eye does.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want to strangle the eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will be strangling the eye, so to speak, because you are identified with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's self-destruct.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only way out that you can see.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even the simile says it's these six animals that they are tied to and they will pull everybody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are the one that should be in charge of the six animals, not be pulled by them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason you're pulled by them is because you cannot cease to identify with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the pull is there, first, you feel like you're being pulled in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you have to start.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start by being pulled, you start by not giving in to the pull, but if all you do is just try to get rid of the pull, you're basically trying to remove the senses, trying to kill the animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: That still doesn't make you in charge.
[SPEAKER_01]: That just kills the animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody says, yeah, I would not see sights with my eyes, that's how I'm free.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would not hear sounds with my ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, well, you're no different than a blind and a deaf man.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not free at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have one animal left pulling you around.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't need six.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enough for one of them to pull you around.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you're alive, you will at least have one, at least your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if all of your senses fail, you're kind of locked inside syndrome or something, you have your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that mind will be pulling you now
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is to you not be pulled through identification with that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to not have the sense pulling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through non-identification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say non-identification, again, it should not be understood like as a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I choose to identify.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not being able to resist the pull, by not having the clear context and perspective in regard to the senses, you are automatically identified.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't just choose to say this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can set yourself up so that you're unable to take it as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you set yourself up by actually sustaining the perspective in regard to the various pulling senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're contrasting now these senses against the better, more wholesome, broader perspective that corresponds closer to the actual universal truth, the real characteristics of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you get to see, oh yeah, truly, these are the five, six wild animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can allow them to run wild and then pay the price as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if it's the same suit or the other suit, but it says, like, if I... if I let this cow go and eat wherever he wants, my ox, if I let it, then, you know, the owner will complain to the police, they'll come and they beat me up, they flog me, they fine me, because it was my bull, I'm responsible for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't let it go and eat anywhere, wherever he wants, so I don't incur suffering on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't get out of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or same like, like as I said, imagine like, you know, you're tied to five dogs, six dogs, and if you allow them, one of them to pull, they will gain the momentum, and then they'll be dragging you around.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to stand.
[SPEAKER_01]: You... and then, if they choose to go through the rocky terrain and thorny terrain, you will.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't... you can't... oh, now I want to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now it's too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will stop when it's running... when it runs... when it runs its course.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by that time, you might be like beaten to death
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of those desires and wild animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, you're not trying to strangle the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to maintain a better perspective in a sense of indirectly know that, oh, if I were to let this sense go out there now, there's a good likelihood it will see something, hear something, taste something.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then result in its increased excitement that then I will have to deal with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's better for me to not allow it, then I don't have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I abide in peace here and now, as opposed to having to then spend all this effort to calm the sense down, calm the animal down.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, just prevent it from being excited in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you do that, the more you maintain that perspective, regardless of what sense is pulling you,
[SPEAKER_01]: The clearer the nature of that relationship with the senses becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, less and less identified with them you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why anāgāmīs and arahants in the suttas, when the Māra would try to tempt them through the senses, they would refer to the six senses, the body, the person.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would say, who are you talking about?
[SPEAKER_01]: None of this is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is just a creature there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still the five, six functioning senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in the same sense, you, from your point of view, would see a dog, a bird, a monkey, another person, and now there is this creature as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a creature there, creature, creature, oh, and there's this creature that's always paired with me, because of which I used to assume it's mine, because there was no other creature as close as this creature, to my point of view, but now I understand that's not mine either.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you should regard it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We usually regard our own creature, our own selves, as our own.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the closest friend, so to speak, the most intimate thing, it's your own thoughts with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, you should regard that also as not yours, as a stranger.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean you well, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the creature is there, you're paired with it, the six senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no choice to be apart from the six senses, but you have a choice whether they get excited or not, and whether you're gonna have to be dealing with it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why he guards the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't chase the sense object or try to get rid of the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't try to shut the eyes down or pull the eyes out or cut the ears off.
[SPEAKER_01]: You guard the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you know before the eye sees ears, hair and so on, is this leading towards lust or towards dispassion, towards anger or towards lack of anger and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it still was lost, you guard the door, you don't let the animal...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, imagine you're holding dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dog is calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you see there is a deer coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dog still hasn't spotted it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Kill the dog quickly, before it sees the deer, so you don't have to deal with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you kill the dog, you kill yourself, because you are the creature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shoot the deer before it comes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, good luck.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would you do in that instance?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here you are, five dogs, both hands, leashes, they are calm, and there is a big, smelly deer coming the way, just behind the bend.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you see it, the dogs don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you turn around, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Turn around, yeah?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you can't turn around... Well, you just get their attention, make them sit down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Set them up, so they're not basically directly exposed to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can't do that either, what would you do then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Tie them.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you hold them on the leashes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You hold them down.
[SPEAKER_01]: You dig your heels in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Twist the leashes twice around your hands and pull down and hold.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, any of those things, the result is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: They must not chase the deer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, for as... until you're beyond sensuality and so on, the animals will get excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't want to be contributing towards that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that whole, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't remember the exact sutra, but when the Buddha says, you know, or you think the opposite, or you think something else, but if you can't do any of that, you crush your mind with the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a drunk man would pin down the weak man until he calms down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if the dogs are now, you couldn't prevent the excitement, as it will inevitably happen at some point, because you didn't foresee the deer soon enough, you were careless, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now they're excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still, it's better to endure and not give in to the pull, than to let it and then become the dogs and get identified with the creature.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you practice that, then the clearer also the danger of allowing it becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when all you're used to is being dragged around and surfing on the leashes of various wild animals, you don't see the danger, because you're just used to the constant movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, that's what you're training them to become.
[SPEAKER_02]: For sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're training them to be wild.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly how the passion works.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha means by diversification, proliferation or multiplying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you choose the singleness of no,
[SPEAKER_01]: As opposed to diversity, of spread in every direction, and then one deer, two deer, six deers, fox, rabbit, squirrel...
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what... people think singleness of mind is with... where you kind of... at the end of this proliferation, you find a point that all proliferation ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Singleness is actually when you undo all the proliferation and find a point before things proliferate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you choose to stay on that level and protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Guarding the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: One entrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: One pointedness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not one-pointed because you stare at the deer, you don't see anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're one-pointed because your point is none of the situation will change, doesn't matter whether deer or squirrel, whatever comes in here, dog will not run.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if they're used to running all the time, they're going to be pulling a lot in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Untrained animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, same with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you haven't been really developing and clarifying perspective in regard to the sensory strength, if you've just been doing it blindly,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still gonna hurt.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once the perspective is there, the singleness of mind, that unity, so to speak, of non-diversified in different direction and so on, remains, even while the sense is excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no identification with it, because there is no perspective loss.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you and the creature, your point of view in regard to the creature, and the thoughts of the creature, and the plans of the creature, and the sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches of the creature,
[SPEAKER_01]: None that's yours, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not to say, oh, no, no, not mine, not mine, to dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not mine, because it's there and I have perspective in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not my dogs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's often the response.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or denial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or acceptance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, well, that's what the dogs do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, but you don't have to suffer on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the trained dog wouldn't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't say that's what all the dogs do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to qualify that statement and say that's what the untrained dogs do, which now highlights you have a choice to train or to untrain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what we say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Untrained eye, untrained ear, untrained senses, untrained mind in regard to the senses, that's what it would do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you train it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take responsibility for the lack of training and train it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the clearer your perspective is, the more it becomes obvious it's an indirect training.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of... Sensory training is actually effortless, if done rightly as well, because it's on the basis of mindfulness, which you can't have too much of, and it is effortless, if done rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do, and even if the excitement happens, it's not your excitement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how much this dog is excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not going anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then it comes down.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might have to hear it, listen to it yapping, but that's the disturbance that you have to accept on the level that arahant accepts the disturbance left on account of this body until the aggregates break apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, for sure, his animals will not be able to pull him anymore, ever again, at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he senses that in his control.
[SPEAKER_02]: The spirit has been broken in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been tamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been well tamed and trained and obedient.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, both are dwelling at ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because senses are happier as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's then the pleasure of jhāna and, you know, touching the pleasure with the body, if the meditation is done correctly and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more pleasant to be peaceful, even for the wild animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they can't help themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by doing so, you're helping yourself as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Training the creature that is you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's exactly like training dogs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's often the similitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taming an elephant, taming an ox, that the Buddha used in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Elephant, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, the difference is whether you're kind of projecting it externally or... No, you have to see it yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your five, six senses as five, six dogs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they all have their different little traits and little characteristics and little kind of preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you are the one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, you don't train them by constantly choking them and holding on to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You train them by seeing more than what they see.
[SPEAKER_01]: By maintaining the background to their own actions that they're not aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, he's running like a maniac now, and there are wild boars there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't see it, and when he does, it will be too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, imagine you're tied to that dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's dragging you where the wild boars are, angry with little babies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so now my life is at stake, so I better do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just... Oh, it's not my problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order to stop identifying with the six animals that your creature is, you have to take them up personally first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to actually see that you are at stake here.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you let your mind run, eyes, ears, nose and so on, you will pay the price, not them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I better take it this personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You end up taking it personally, you tame them eventually, and then you cannot identify with them, because you can't lose perspective now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And patience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's the key.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's any... even the basic dog training.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first thing they say, you must be patient.
[SPEAKER_01]: And imagine how much more, when it comes to training yourself as a creature of the six.
[SPEAKER_02]: The wild man.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the wild man.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, everybody's a wild creature, yeah.